export default data = [
  {
    question:
      "When was the IPA Declaration of the Child’s Right to Play originally produced?",
    options: [
      "November 1977",
      "November 1989",
      "November 1982",
      "November 1979",
    ],
    correct_option: "November 1977",
  },
  {
    question: "Why is play important for children according to IPA?",
    options: [
      "It helps children win games",
      "It helps children develop physically, mentally, and emotionally",
      "It helps children to get good grades",
      "It helps children to stay indoors",
    ],
    correct_option:
      "It helps children develop physically, mentally, and emotionally",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which article of the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child emphasizes the child's right to leisure, play, and participation in cultural and artistic activities?",
    options: ["Article 30", "Article 29", "Article 31", "Article 32"],
    correct_option: "Article 31",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which organization is responsible for advocating for the promotion of play opportunities based on the IPA Declaration?",
    options: [
      "UNESCO",
      "IPA (International Play Association)",
      "UNICEF",
      "WHO",
    ],
    correct_option: "IPA (International Play Association)",
  },
  {
    question: "What does IPA say about the role of play in education?",
    options: [
      "Play is not part of education",
      "Play should be limited to weekends",
      "Play is part of education and helps in learning",
      "Play is only for younger children",
    ],
    correct_option: "Play is part of education and helps in learning",
  },
];

export const EducationData = [
  {
    question: "When was Article 21-A added to the Constitution of India?",
    options: ["2009", "2010", "2002", "2005"],
    correct_option: "2002",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What age group does Article 21-A focus on for free and compulsory education?",
    options: ["4-12 years", "6-14 years", "5-15 years", "7-13 years"],
    correct_option: "6-14 years",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When did the Right of Children to Free and Compulsory Education (RTE) Act start?",
    options: ["2005", "2009", "2010", "2002"],
    correct_option: "2010",
  },
  {
    question: "What does the RTE Act say about school fees?",
    options: [
      "Schools can charge any amount",
      "No fees for government-supported schools",
      "Fees are decided by parents",
      "Schools can charge as per their choice",
    ],
    correct_option: "No fees for government-supported schools",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is responsible for ensuring schools have enough trained teachers according to the RTE Act?",
    options: ["Parents", "School management", "Government", "Students"],
    correct_option: "Government",
  },
];

export const WorkingData = [
  {
    question: "What does the Child Labour Act, 1986, prohibit?",
    options: [
      "Children below 10 years to work",
      "Children below 14 years to work",
      "Children below 16 years to work",
      "Children below 18 years to work",
    ],
    correct_option: "Children below 14 years to work",
  },
  {
    questio:
      "According to Section 7 (4) of the act, between which hours are children not allowed to work?",
    options: [
      "5 p.m. - 6 a.m.",
      "6 p.m. - 7 a.m.",
      "7 p.m. - 8 a.m.",
      "8 p.m. - 9 a.m.",
    ],
    correct_option: "7 p.m. - 8 a.m.",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the Child Labour Act, 1986 renamed to?",
    options: [
      "Child Welfare Act",
      "Child Protection Act",
      "Child and Adolescent Labour Act",
      "Child Rights Act",
    ],
    correct_option: "Child and Adolescent Labour Act",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Has India ratified the International Labour Organization's Worst forms of Child Labour Convention, 1999?",
    options: ["Yes", "No", "Partially", "Not mentioned"],
    correct_option: "No",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What did the 2016 Amendment Act change regarding the definition of a 'child'?",
    options: [
      "A person who has not completed 10 years",
      "A person who has not completed 12 years",
      "A person who has not completed 14 years",
      "A person who has not completed 16 years",
    ],
    correct_option: "A person who has not completed 14 years",
  },
];

export const LifeData = [
  {
    question: "What is the right to life?",
    options: [
      "The chance to have fun",
      "The right to grow up and become adults",
      "The right to play",
      "The right to study",
    ],
    correct_option: "The right to grow up and become adults",
  },
  {
    question: "What does the right to life mean for children from birth?",
    options: [
      "The right to have fun",
      "The right to be protected",
      "The right to have toys",
      "The right to go to school",
    ],
    correct_option: "The right to be protected",
  },
  {
    question: "What does the right to life protect against?",
    options: ["Being hungry", "Being sick", "Being killed", "Being scolded"],
    correct_option: "Being killed",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What does the right to life imply for countries regarding children?",
    options: [
      "To give them toys",
      "To give them candies",
      "Not to subject them to the death penalty",
      "To let them play all day",
    ],
    correct_option: "Not to subject them to the death penalty",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What should countries actively fight against and condemn for children?",
    options: [
      "Acts of kindness",
      "Acts of infanticide",
      "Acts of sharing",
      "Acts of playing",
    ],
    correct_option: "Acts of infanticide",
  },
];

export const HealthData = [
  {
    question: "What is the fundamental right of every child?",
    options: [
      "Right to education",
      "Right to play",
      "Right to health",
      "Right to freedom",
    ],
    correct_option: "Right to health",
  },
  {
    question: "What does Article 24 of the UNCRC emphasize?",
    options: [
      "Importance of education",
      "Importance of healthcare for children",
      "Importance of play",
      "Importance of freedom",
    ],
    correct_option: "Importance of healthcare for children",
  },
  {
    question: "What does ensuring a child's health involve?",
    options: [
      "Healthcare access and nutrition",
      "Play and freedom",
      "Education and play",
      "Freedom and nutrition",
    ],
    correct_option: "Healthcare access and nutrition",
  },
  {
    question: "What should governments prioritize for children's health?",
    options: [
      "High-quality education",
      "Access to nutritious food and clean environment",
      "Freedom to play",
      "Access to high-tech gadgets",
    ],
    correct_option: "Access to nutritious food and clean environment",
  },
  {
    question: "What does Article 24 say about children's right to health?",
    options: [
      "Protection from work",
      "Protection from hazardous conditions",
      "Both physical and mental well-being",
      "Only physical well-being",
    ],
    correct_option: "Both physical and mental well-being",
  },
];

export const Hindidata = [
    {
      question:
        "बच्चों के खेलने के अधिकार के IPA घोषणा कब बनाई गई थी?",
      options: [
        "नवंबर 1977",
        "नवंबर 1989",
        "नवंबर 1982",
        "नवंबर 1979",
      ],
      correct_option: "नवंबर 1977",
    },
    {
      question: "IPA के अनुसार खेल क्यों महत्वपूर्ण है बच्चों के लिए?",
      options: [
        "बच्चों को खेल जीतना है",
        "बच्चों की शारीरिक, मानसिक और भावनात्मक विकास के लिए",
        "बच्चों को अच्छे अंक मिलने के लिए",
        "बच्चों को घर में रहने के लिए",
      ],
      correct_option:
        "बच्चों की शारीरिक, मानसिक और भावनात्मक विकास के लिए",
    },
    {
      question:
        "UN Convention on the Rights of the Child के कौन से अनुच्छेद बच्चों के खेल, सांस्कृतिक और कला क्रियाओं में भाग लेने के अधिकार को जोर देते हैं?",
      options: ["अनुच्छेद 30", "अनुच्छेद 29", "अनुच्छेद 31", "अनुच्छेद 32"],
      correct_option: "अनुच्छेद 31",
    },
    {
      question:
        "किस संगठन का काम है IPA घोषणा के आधार पर खेल के अवसरों को बढ़ाना?",
      options: [
        "UNESCO",
        "IPA (International Play Association)",
        "UNICEF",
        "WHO",
      ],
      correct_option: "IPA (International Play Association)",
    },
    {
      question: "IPA शिक्षा में खेल का क्या कहती है?",
      options: [
        "खेल शिक्षा का हिस्सा नहीं है",
        "खेल सिर्फ weekends के लिए है",
        "खेल शिक्षा का हिस्सा है और पढ़ने में मदद करता है",
        "खेल सिर्फ छोटे बच्चों के लिए है",
      ],
      correct_option: "खेल शिक्षा का हिस्सा है और पढ़ने में मदद करता है",
    },
  ];
  
  export const HindiEducationData = [
    {
      question: "भारतीय संविधान में Article 21-A कब जोड़ा गया था?",
      options: ["2009", "2010", "2002", "2005"],
      correct_option: "2002",
    },
    {
      question:
        "नि: शुल्क और अनिवार्य शिक्षा के लिए Article 21-A किस आयु समूह पर ध्यान केंद्रित करता है?",
      options: ["4-12 साल", "6-14 साल", "5-15 साल", "7-13 साल"],
      correct_option: "6-14 साल",
    },
    {
      question:
        "बच्चों के नि: शुल्क और अनिवार्य शिक्षा का कब शुरू हुआ?",
      options: ["2005", "2009", "2010", "2002"],
      correct_option: "2010",
    },
    {
      question: "RTE अधिनियम शैक्षणिक शुल्क के बारे में क्या कहता है?",
      options: [
        "स्कूल किसी भी राशि का वसूल कर सकते हैं",
        "सरकार द्वारा समर्थित स्कूलों के लिए कोई शुल्क नहीं",
        "शुल्क माता-पिता द्वारा निर्धारित होता है",
        "स्कूल अपनी पसंद के अनुसार शुल्क ले सकते हैं",
      ],
      correct_option: "सरकार द्वारा समर्थित स्कूलों के लिए कोई शुल्क नहीं",
    },
    {
      question:
        "RTE अधिनियम के अनुसार स्कूलों को पर्याप्त प्रशिक्षित शिक्षक होने की जिम्मेदारी किसे है?",
      options: ["माता-पिता", "स्कूल प्रबंधन", "सरकार", "छात्र"],
      correct_option: "सरकार",
    },
  ];
  
  export const HindiWorkingData = [
    {
      question: "Child Labour Act, 1986 क्या प्रतिबंधित करता है?",
      options: [
        "10 साल से कम आयु के बच्चों को काम करना",
        "14 साल से कम आयु के बच्चों को काम करना",
        "16 साल से कम आयु के बच्चों को काम करना",
        "18 साल से कम आयु के बच्चों को काम करना",
      ],
      correct_option: "14 साल से कम आयु के बच्चों को काम करना",
    },
    {
      question:
        "अधिनियम के अनुसार Section 7 (4), बच्चों को किस समय नहीं काम करने दिया जाता है?",
      options: [
        "5 बजे शाम - 6 बजे सुबह",
        "6 बजे शाम - 7 बजे सुबह",
        "7 बजे शाम - 8 बजे सुबह",
        "8 बजे शाम - 9 बजे सुबह",
      ],
      correct_option: "7 बजे शाम - 8 बजे सुबह",
    },
    {
      question: "Child Labour Act, 1986 का नाम क्या था?",
      options: [
        "Child Welfare Act",
        "Child Protection Act",
        "Child and Adolescent Labour Act",
        "Child Rights Act",
      ],
      correct_option: "Child and Adolescent Labour Act",
    },
    {
      question:
        "क्या भारत ने International Labour Organization का Worst forms of Child Labour Convention, 1999 को अनुमोदित किया है?",
      options: ["हाँ", "नहीं", "आंशिक", "उल्लेख नहीं है"],
      correct_option: "नहीं",
    },
    {
      question:
        "2016 संशोधन अधिनियम ने 'बच्चा' की परिभाषा में क्या परिवर्तन किया?",
      options: [
        "जिसने 10 साल पूरे नहीं किए हैं",
        "जिसने 12 साल पूरे नहीं किए हैं",
        "जिसने 14 साल पूरे नहीं किए हैं",
        "जिसने 16 साल पूरे नहीं किए हैं",
      ],
      correct_option: "जिसने 14 साल पूरे नहीं किए हैं",
    },
  ];
  
  export const HindiLifeData = [
    {
      question: "जीवन का अधिकार क्या है?",
      options: [
        "मजे करने का मौका",
        "बड़े होकर बच्चों के बनने का हक",
        "खेलने का हक",
        "पढ़ाई का हक",
      ],
      correct_option: "बड़े होकर बच्चों के बनने का हक",
    },
    {
      question: "जन्म से बच्चों के जीवन के लिए जीवन का हक क्या है?",
      options: [
        "मजे करने का हक",
        "संरक्षित होने का हक",
        "खिलौने होने का हक",
        "स्कूल जाने का हक",
      ],
      correct_option: "संरक्षित होने का हक",
    },
    {
      question: "जीवन के हक किस चीज से बचाव करता है?",
      options: ["भूख से", "बीमारी से", "मौत से", "डाँट से"],
      correct_option: "मौत से",
    },
    {
      question:
        "देशों के लिए जीवन के हक क्या दावा करता है?",
      options: [
        "उन्हें खिलौने देना",
        "उन्हें कैंडीज़ देना",
        "उन्हें मौत की सजा न देना",
        "उन्हें पूरे दिन खेलने देना",
      ],
      correct_option: "उन्हें मौत की सजा न देना",
    },
    {
      question:
        "देशों को बच्चों के लिए क्या काम करना चाहिए?",
      options: [
        "अच्छाई के कार्य",
        "बच्चों के खिलाने",
        "बाँटने के कार्य",
        "खेलने के कार्य",
      ],
      correct_option: "अच्छाई के कार्य",
    },
  ];
  
  export const HindiHealthData = [
    {
      question: "हर बच्चे का मौलिक अधिकार क्या है?",
      options: [
        "शिक्षा का हक",
        "खेलने का हक",
        "स्वास्थ्य का हक",
        "स्वतंत्रता का हक",
      ],
      correct_option: "स्वास्थ्य का हक",
    },
    {
      question: "UNCRC के Article 24 में क्या जोर दिया गया है?",
      options: [
        "शिक्षा के महत्व",
        "बच्चों के स्वास्थ्य के महत्व",
        "खेल के महत्व",
        "स्वतंत्रता के महत्व",
      ],
      correct_option: "बच्चों के स्वास्थ्य के महत्व",
    },
    {
      question: "बच्चे के स्वास्थ्य की सुनिश्चित करने में क्या शामिल है?",
      options: [
        "स्वास्थ्य सेवा और पोषण",
        "खेल और स्वतंत्रता",
        "शिक्षा और खेल",
        "स्वतंत्रता और पोषण",
      ],
      correct_option: "स्वास्थ्य सेवा और पोषण",
    },
    {
      question: "सरकारें बच्चों के स्वास्थ्य के लिए क्या प्राथमिकता देनी चाहिए?",
      options: [
        "उच्च गुणवत्ता वाली शिक्षा",
        "पोषण युक्त भोजन और साफ वातावरण",
        "खेलने की स्वतंत्रता",
        "उच्च-तकनीकी उपकरणों का पहुंच",
      ],
      correct_option: "पोषण युक्त भोजन और साफ वातावरण",
    },
    {
      question: "Article 24 में बच्चों के स्वास्थ्य के हक के बारे में क्या कहा गया है?",
      options: [
        "काम से संरक्षण",
        "जोखिमपूर्ण स्थितियों से संरक्षण",
        "केवल शारीरिक स्वास्थ्य",
        "शारीरिक और मानसिक स्वास्थ्य दोनों",
      ],
      correct_option: "शारीरिक और मानसिक स्वास्थ्य दोनों",
    },
  ];
  

